# **Yassine Laguel**

CONTACT INFORMATION

Management Sciences and Information Systems Dept. **Rutgers University** 

100 Rockafellar Road, Rutgers Business School

New Brunswick, NJ 08854, USA

Phone: +1-732-374-5936

Mail: yassine.laguel@rutgers.edu https://yassine-laguel.github.io

RESEARCH **INTERESTS**  My interests center around optimization under uncertainty and its applications in stochastic programming and machine learning. A common thread in my research is the design and analysis of numerical algorithms to address risk in data-driven applications. I draw and extend ideas and tools from convex optimization, probability theory and numerical analysis while keeping an operational approach, with a balance between theoretical and practical contributions.

ACADEMIC **POSITIONS** 

# **Princeton University**,

Aug 2022 - Present

Departmental Guest at the Center for Statistics and Machine Learning (CSML). Princeton, USA.

Rutgers University,

Jan 2022 - Present

Postdoctoral Associate at the Department of Management Sciences and Information Systems (MSIS), hosted by Prof. Mert Gürbüzbalaban.

New Brunswick, USA.

**EDUCATION** 

# Ph.D. in Optimization and Machine Learning,

Oct 2018 - Nov 2021

Supervised by Jérôme Malick, Université Grenoble Alpes, Grenoble, France.

#### B.S., M.S. in Computer Sciences and Applied Mathematics

Sep 2015 - Sep 2018

Diplôme d'ingénieur from ENSIMAG, Grenoble France.

#### **B.S.**, M.S. in Mathematics

Sep 2015 - Sep 2018

Master major in statistics, Université Grenoble Alpes, Grenoble, France. Degrees pursued in parallel to my diplôme d'ingénieur.

JOURNAL PAPERS

- [1] Yassine Laguel, Mert Gürbüzbalaban, Necdet Serhat Aybat. A risk-averse perspective on acceleration for saddle point problems (Tentative title). *In preparation*.
- [2] Yu-Guan Hsieh, Yassine Laguel, Franck Iutzeler, Jérôme Malick. Push-pull with device sampling. IEEE Transactions in Automatic Control. 2022. Under review.
- [3] Yassine Laguel, Krishna Pillutla, Jérôme Malick, Zaid Harchaoui. Federated learning with heterogeneous data: a superquantile optimization approach. Machine Learning Journal. 2022. Under review.
- [4] Yassine Laguel, Wim Van Ackooij, Jérôme Malick. Chance constrained problems: a bilevel convex optimization perspective. Computational Optimization and Applications. 2022. Under review.
- [5] Yassine Laguel. Risk-averse optimization: models, algorithms, and applications in machine learning. PhD. Manuscript. 2022.
- [6] Yassine Laguel, Jérôme Malick, Zaid Harchaoui. Superquantile-based learning: a direct approach using gradient-based optimization. Journal of Signal Processing Systems. No. 94, pages 161-177. 2022. https://yassine-laguel.github.io/files/2021\_jsps.pdf

- [7] Yassine Laguel, Wim Van Ackooij, Jérôme Malick, Guilherme Matiussi Ramalho. On the convexity of level-sets of probability functions. *Journal of Convex Analysis*. No. 29.2, pages 411-442. 2022. https://yassine-laguel.github.io/files/transconcavity-paper.pdf
- [8] Yassine Laguel, Krishna Pillutla, Jérôme Malick, Zaid Harchaoui. Superquantiles at work: machine learning applications and efficient (sub)gradient computation. Set-Valued and Variational Analysis. No. 29, pages 967–996. 2022. https://yassine-laguel. github.io/files/svaa-paper.pdf.
- [9] Gilles Bareilles, Yassine Laguel, Dmitry Grishchenko, Franck Iutzeler, Jerome Malick. Randomized progressive hedging methods for multi-stage stochastic programming. *Annals of Operations Research*. No. 295, pages 535–560. 2020. https://arxiv.org/abs/2009.12186

### CONFERENCE PAPERS

- [10] Yassine Laguel, Krishna Pillutla, Jérôme Malick, Zaid Harchaoui. Device heterogeneity in federated learning: a superquantile approach. Proceedings of the 55<sup>th</sup> Annual Conference on Information Sciences and Systems (CISS 2021). https://arxiv.org/abs/2002. 11223
- [11] Yassine Laguel, Jérôme Malick, Zaid Harchaoui. First order optimization for superquantile-based supervised learning. *Proceedings of the Machine Learning and Signal Processing Conference (MLSP 2020) Best Student Paper Award.* https://arxiv.org/abs/2009.14575

SOFTWARE TACO 2022

Python toolbox for chance constrained optimization. Yassine Laguel, Wim Van Ackooij, Jérôme Malick. https://yassine-laguel.github.io/taco/.

**SPQR** 2020

Python toolbox for superquantile minimization. Yassine Laguel, Jérôme Malick, Zaid Harchaoui.https://yassine-laguel.github.io/spqr/.

#### RandomizedProgressiveHedging.jl

2019

Julia toolbox for solving multistage stochastic problems by randomized versions of the progressive hedging algorithm. Gilles Bareilles, Yassine Laguel, Dmitry Grishchenko, Franck Iutzeler, Jerome Malick

#### INVITED TALKS

# On the acceleration/robustness trade-off for stochastic min-max problems

• INFORMS Annual Meeting

2022

A robust perspective on acceleration for saddle point problems *Talk*. Indianapolis, USA.

• International conference on continuous optimization (ICCOPT)

2022

New perspectives on robustness via the Conditional Value at Risk. *Talk.* Lehigh, USA.

### Handling statistical heterogeneity in federated learning

• Magnet Seminar

2022

Federated learning with heterogeneous data: a superquantile optimization approach. *Talk.* Inria Lille, France.

• University of Washington Machine Learning Seminar 2022 Convex risk measures: models, algorithms and applications in federated learning. *Talk*. Seattle, USA.

• Thoth Seminar 2022 Convex risk measures: models, algorithms and applications in federated learning.

Convex risk measures: models, algorithms and applications in federated learning. *Talk*. Inria Grenoble, France.

Journées des Statistiques     Risk-sensitive learning for heterogeneous frameworks.  Tall. Nico. Erappo.	2021
<ul> <li>Talk. Nice, France.</li> <li>Workshop on Communication Efficient Distributed Optimization Device heterogeneity in federated learning: a superquantile approach.</li> </ul>	2021
<ul> <li>Poster Online workshop.</li> <li>Federated Learning One World Seminar Device heterogeneity in federated learning: a superquantile approach. Talk. Online Seminar.</li> </ul>	2020
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=W-oNzU04Y8I  Optimization for Machine Learning Conference Handling device heterogeneity in federated learning.  Poster. Marseille, France.	2020
<b>PhD. Defense</b> Risk-averse optimization: models, algorithms, and applications in machine learning. <i>Talk</i> . Grenoble, France.	2021
<ul> <li>Hidden convexity in probabilistic programming</li> <li>ANSI Seminar</li> <li>On hidden convexity in chance constrained problems.</li> <li>Talk. Los Alamos, USA.</li> </ul>	2021
<ul> <li>SMAI-MODE Conference         A DC approach for chance constraints.     </li> <li>Talk. Saclay, France.</li> </ul>	2020
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KB3sV-trEy4&list  • International conference on continuous optimization (ICCOPT)  On the interplay between generalized concavity and chance constraints.  Talk. Berlin, Germany.	2019
<ul> <li>Efficient oracles for distributionally robust optimization</li> <li>IFDS Workshop on Distributional Robustness in Data Science SPQR: A Toolbox for Superquantile-based Learning Talk. Seattle, USA.</li> </ul>	2022
<ul> <li>Machine Learning and Signal Processing Conference (MLSP)         First-order optimization for superquantile-based supervised learning.         Best student Paper Award. Talk. Espoo, Finland.     </li> </ul>	2020
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JRWvWxOxRiQ  • ROADEF  Practical minimization of CVar-based risk functions.  Talk. Montpellier, France.	2020
• International conference on stochastic programming (ICSP)  1 <sup>st</sup> -order methods for minimization of superquantile-based risk measures.  Talk. Trondheim, Norway.	2019
Instructor	
<ul> <li>Fundamentals of analysis and algebra.</li> <li>Grenoble INP. <i>Undergraduate Course</i>. Grenoble, France.</li> </ul>	50h.
<ul> <li>Fundamentals of analysis and algebra.</li> </ul>	50h.
Unversité Grenoble Alpes. <i>Undergraduate Course</i> . Grenoble, France.  • Introduction to R.	2x30h.
Université Grenoble Alpes. Undergraduate Course. Grenoble, France.	
• Introduction to Python.  Université Grenoble Alpes. <i>Graduate Course</i> . Grenoble, France.	2x30h.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

18h. • Convex and distributed optimization. Université Grenoble Alpes. Graduate Course. Grenoble, France. • Numerical optimization. 25h. ENSIMAG. Graduate Course. Grenoble, France. **Guest Lecturer** • Distributionally robust machine learning. 4h. University of Washington. Graduate Course. Seattle, USA. • Introduction to federated learning. 1.5h. ENSIMAG. Graduate Course. Grenoble, France. **PROFESSIONAL Committee Service** SERVICE • Founder and Organizer of the Optim & ML Seminar at Rutgers University, since March 2022. • Founder and Organizer of GORGeous (Grenoble Optimization Reading Group), at the Université Grenoble Alpes, from Sep. 2019 to Oct. 2021. https://sites.google.com/view/gorgeous-optim/ • Jury member for the International Tournament of Young Mathematicians (ITYM). Iasi, Romania. 2012. Referee Service • Journal of Machine Learning Research (JMLR) • Mathematics of Operations Research • EURO Journal on Computational Optimization • Automatica • Optimization • *Journal of Optimization Theory and Applications (JOTA)* **Conference Service** • Program Committee: 51st International Conference on Parallel Processing (ICPP 2022). • Organizer of the session First-order methods for min-max problems at ICCOPT 2022. • Organizer of the session First-order methods for minimax problems at INFORMS 2022. PROFESSIONAL **Research Internships** EXPERIENCE • University of Washington, Seattle, USA. 2018 Initiated the series of works [6, 8, 10, 11]. EDF R&D, Saclay, France. 2017. Led to the publication of the journal paper [7]. • WeSave, Financial Startup in Paris, France. 2016 Worked on the establishment of quantitative criterion based on random correlations matrices to predict crises. **Consulting Activity** 2016 • Conception and development of a transport management software for an international firm. **Best Student Paper Award** 2020 **AWARDS** Machine learning and signal processing conference (MLSP 2020). Espoo, Finland. Finalist of the International Tournament of Young Mathematicians (ITYM) 2012  $Rank: 3^{rd}$ . Orsay, France. Winner of the french tournament of young mathematicians (TFJM) 2012

Saclay, France.